<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abbreviat of the depositions of the witnesses, adduced by the Earl of Lauderdale against the Earl of Aberdene.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A70BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173257</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01492)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2749:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abbreviat of the depositions of the witnesses, adduced by the Earl of Lauderdale against the Earl of Aberdene.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aberdeen, George Gordon, --  Earl of, 1637-1720.</term>
               <term>Lauderdale, John Maitland, --  Duke of, 1616-1682.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175738:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ABBREVIAT</hi> Of the Depoſitions of the Witneſſes, Adduced by the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> against the Earl of <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> when he was only Preſident of the Seſſion, and neither Chancellor nor Officer of State, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured and wrote for a Commiſſion, for the Tryal of the Mint.</p>
            <p>The Viſcount of <hi>Tarbat</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> did write out of <hi>England</hi> to the Deponent, to haſte up a Commiſſion for Tryal of the Mint, and that accordingly the Deponent did ſend up a Draught of a Commiſſion, and thinks he has ſome Letters to that purpoſe, but at preſent cannot find them out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> was going to <hi>London,</hi> and that the Earl had obtained his Majeſties leave to that effect; Yet the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> was ſo earneſt in the proſecution of the Commiſſion of the Mint, that he refuſed to let him go.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Queensberry</hi> in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones, he was preſent when the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> offered to take leave of the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> but what paſt betwixt them, he did not know, only he minds, that the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> told him, that he had refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to let him go up, till the buſineſs of the Mint ſhould be over, and cannot be poſitive, whether the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> called a Council, or a <hi>Quorum</hi> of the Commiſſion of the Mint, but one of them he believes was called, and that a Clerk was ſent to order his ſtay, to attend the Commiſſion of the Mint.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> had a proſpect and deſign the time of that Commiſſion; and before the raiſing of the Proceſs for the benefite of the event thereof, and that he dealt for the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Viſcount of <hi>Tarbat</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>5th.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That <hi>Aberdene</hi> did recommend to the Deponent (when he was going to Court) his Affairs in general, and to ſpeak to the King in his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which the Deponent did; but the Deponent had no Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from <hi>Aberdene</hi> anent the Mint in ſpecial; And Depones, That the Deponent underſtanding, that the Mony due upon the Mint was to be exacted; he propoſed the ſame to the King, in ſavours of <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dene,</hi> albeit he had not any ſpecial Commiſſion for it; but what was the King's Majeſties Anſwer, the Deponent conceives he is not holden, and is not free to condeſcend thereon.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>8th.</hi> Interrogator he Anſwers, That as to what paſt in privat betwixt the King's Majeſty and the Deponent, he refuſes to anſwer; but as to a Letter ſent to, or received from the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175738:2"/>That he did acquaint the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> of the Deponent,<note place="margin">This was before the raiſing of the Mint-Proceſs.</note> his propoſing to the King, that the Earl might have a Gift of what was due upon the Mint, and that this was in the Harveſt time, 1682. And that <hi>Aberdene</hi> did write, and return Thanks to the Deponent, for making the propoſal in his behalf, which Letters the Deponent thinks he hath, but cannot at preſent find them out.</p>
            <p>The then Lord Chancellor in the midſt of his Anſwer to the <hi>4th.</hi> Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator, Depones, That the firſt ſuſpicion he had, that the Earl of <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dene</hi> had intereſt in that Affair, as to his own particular, was, when the Vote was put concerning <hi>John Falconer</hi> the Warden his Depoſition, whether it did prove ſufficiently, or not; and when that Vote was like to miſcarry, as to <hi>Aberdene</hi>'s intention in it; <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſaid to the Lords, that if this was the way they ſerved the King, they who were the King's Judges, (or to this purpoſe) that he would be forced to let the King know of it: To which the Lord <hi>Pitmedden</hi> Anſwered, That he wiſhed the King were amongſt the Lords, to Judge of their carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; that then the Deponent began to ſuſpect that <hi>Aberdene</hi> had ſome particular intereſt in it, not having obſerved formerly, that the King's buſineſs made him ſo forward.</p>
            <p>Collonel <hi>Grahame</hi> to the firſt and ſecond, Depones, That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, and the Duke of <hi>Queensberrie</hi> Lord Theſaurer, imployed the Deponent upon ſome publick Accompts, and at the ſame time the Deponent was imployed by them to move the late King, and King <hi>James</hi> (then Duke) ſome things relating to their preſent pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Affairs, and particularly for a Gift in favours of the Earl of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdene,</hi> of 1000 <hi>lib. Sterling</hi> a year, or 20000 <hi>lib. Sterling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This was during the dependance of the Proceſs.</note> which was thought to be equivalent; and before the Deponent went out of <hi>Scotland</hi> (being about the end of <hi>February</hi> 1683.) he went to my Lord Theſaurer's Lodging, and had his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance upon the matter, as to the quantity; after which, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent went to my Lord <hi>Aberdene,</hi> and acquainted him with it, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muned with him upon the different Fonds, that it could be made out of; and amongſt others, that of the Mint. But whether or not <hi>Aberdene,</hi> or the Deponent propoſed it firſt, the Deponent cannot be poſitive, but remembers particularly, that when the Deponent propoſed, that in caſe the Lands of <hi>Dudhope</hi> were taken from the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> the Houſe, Parks, and Conſtabulary of <hi>Dundee,</hi> ſhould be given to the Deponent by the King; that the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> anſwered to this purpoſe, that he ſhould be very well content, but that he heard, it will be little uſeful to either of them, becauſe they were reſolved to part with nothing; however he allowed the Deponent to ask that Gift of the 20000 <hi>lib. Sterling,</hi> as freely out of that Fond, as out of any other; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the Deponent, when he came to <hi>New-mercat,</hi> where the late King, and King <hi>James</hi> were for the time, he did repreſent to the King, (and then Duke) the Services of the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> and endeavoured to perſwade his Royal Highneſs to gratifie him with ſome conſiderable Gift, and particularly with 20000 <hi>lib. Sterling,</hi> and told his Highneſs, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Fonds might be found for it, ſuch as the Fines, and the Decreet of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175738:2"/>the Mint; all which his Royal Highneſs heard, and ſaid, he would ſpeak to the King about it; and als far as the Deponent can remember, he ſaid further, when my Lord <hi>Middletoun</hi> came, he would ſee ſomething done, and this the Deponent did ſignifie from <hi>New-mercat,</hi> by a Letter to the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> the <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 1683, and Depones, That when he ſpoke to the Earl of <hi>Midletoun,</hi> to ſavour himſelf anent the Houſe and Parks of <hi>Dudhope,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Midletoun</hi> Anſwered that he could not do it without <hi>Aberdenes</hi> Conſent, and ſaid ſomething as if he had been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways engaged to him in it; and ſo ſoon as the Decreet of the Mint came up, the King having given Warrand of before, a Letter was drawn by the Advice of the Earl of <hi>Midletoun,</hi> and the Deponent who beſt knew the Lands, and the nature of the Gift, ordering the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> to diſpone the ſaids Lands, as is more fully expreſt in the Letter for that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, direct to the Lord High Theſaurer; But withal, the Deponent declares als far as he remembers, he had no advice from the Earl of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdene</hi> thereanent; but after he gave him an accompt what was done, he had his approbation.</p>
            <p>The Depoſition bears, That <hi>Aberdene</hi> had written to the Deponent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Letters, wherein were publick concerns, which he produced, but only read theſe parts thereof that concerns this Affair.</p>
            <p>The firſt Letter is without a date, and bears theſe words; <hi>I</hi> hope you do not think <hi>I</hi> am leſs ſenſible of your kindneſs, that <hi>I</hi> doubt of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Mint affair, ſince both the Earl of <hi>Middletoun</hi> and your ſelf, are of a <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> mind, and ſay only this, That <hi>I</hi> could not do half ſo much for my ſelf, were <hi>I</hi> preſent: This Letter makes mention, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdene</hi> had received one from the Deponent of the laſt of <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Letter is dated the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> thus, The Duke has asked no opinion of me, but what he ſhould do in the Affair of the Mint, and als hard to give you advice at this diſtance anent it, not knowing what may be his Majeſties, or the Dukes purpoſe therein, further than that you ſhould chearfully comply with what you ſee is their inclination.</p>
            <p>The <hi>3d.</hi> Letter is dated the 24 of <hi>March,</hi> which being torn, there could be no more read of it than follows; <hi>I</hi> could not but let you know that <hi>I</hi> would be very well ſatisfied in what you do for your ſelf anent 1. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and Juriſdiction ye wrote of, and do thank you for your care in my Concerns. 2. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> think that project will be little uſeful 3. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> you or me, for they are reſolved 4. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on that accompt; and the Deponent thinks ſo far as he remembers, that the words that are wanting and torn of the Letter, has been theſe, Firſt, (anent the Houſe) The <hi>2d.</hi> is, <hi>(I)</hi> The third (uſeful for) And the <hi>4th</hi> (to part with nothing, or do nothing on that account) And upon the other ſide of the ſame Piece of the Torn Letter, ſwa far as the Deponent can make ſenſe thereof, it's to this purpoſe, I ſhall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your Letter more Particularly by the next; The Lands about <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee</hi> and the reſt, are not of that valued Rent you write, and <hi>Tweedale</hi> Leads the Teinds of <hi>Innerkeithing,</hi> nor would <hi>I</hi> have ſo much ſtreſs laid upon that Project, if his Majeſty ſhould pleaſe to make effectual for me, that which you name, in any way he ſeems fit (which the Deponent thinks he meant to be the 20000 <hi>lib.</hi>) <hi>I</hi> ſhall think my ſelf very much obliged to my Lord <hi>Middletoun</hi> and your ſelf, and am very well ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with your own ſucceſs that way.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:175738:3"/>
            <p>To the <hi>7th.</hi> Depones, he never heard his preſent Majeſty tell his own Thoughts concerning my Lord <hi>Aberdene,</hi> his being both Judge and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and what has paſt beſides in Diſcourſe betwixt the preſent King's Majeſty and the Deponent, the Deponent conceives he is not holden to give an accompt thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> took unwarrantable Courſes in the Tryal, and Proceſs of the Mint, which is evinced in theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> gave <hi>ſpes veniae</hi> to Sir <hi>John Falconer,</hi> to Depone againſt the Earl of <hi>Landerdale,</hi> and aſſurance of keeping of his place.</p>
            <p>My Lord Chancellor Depones, in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, That he has very often heard my Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſay in general, That any Officer of the Mint, who would make Diſcoveries of my Lord <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale</hi>'s Malverſation, would do the King good and acceptable Service; and that <hi>Aberdene</hi> often has ſaid to the Deponent, that if he would ſpeak to Sir <hi>John Falconer,</hi> to make ſuch diſcoveries, Sir <hi>John</hi> might expect great favour in his own particular.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to the <hi>3d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That the Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſs</hi> has often told the Deponent, that he had a Warrand from my Lord <hi>Aberdene,</hi> to give aſſurance of Indemnity to Sir <hi>John Falconer,</hi> if he would inform againſt the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and that the Deponent has juſt ground to believe, that the Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſs</hi> gave a very fuil aſſurance of Indemnity in the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi>'s name.</p>
            <p>The Viſcount of <hi>Tarbat</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>3d</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That he heard the Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſs,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Perth</hi> ſeveral times ſay, that they were warranted to give aſſurance to Sir <hi>John Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner,</hi> if he would confeſs all that he knew concerning the Mint, and that it ſhould not prejudge himſelf.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Reidfoord</hi> in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, Depones, That Sir <hi>John Falconer</hi> having compeared at the Bar, and offered to ſpeak in that affair, to the beſt of the Deponents memory, my Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> told him from the Bench, that if he took that courſe, he behoved to take his hazard of the iſſue, or ſomething to that purpoſe, but does not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber if Sir <hi>John Falconer</hi> did appear thereafter.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, Depones, That Sir <hi>John Falconer</hi> did offer to ſpeak for himſelf, and did ſpeak, but if he was interrupted, the Deponent remembers not.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Falconer</hi> Depones moſt fully in this particular, That he was ſeveral times dealt with by the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> himſelf, and by the Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſs,</hi> at <hi>Aberdene</hi>'s deſire, to Depone againſt the Earl of <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> behaved himſelf with great concern in the Proceſs.</p>
            <p>My Lord Chancellor's Depoſition to the <hi>4th.</hi> Interrogator, which is inſert in the Probation of the <hi>2d.</hi> Article, is repeated likewiſe in this place.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Queensberrie</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175738:3"/>That he obſerved the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi>'s zeal in that, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other matters before the Seſſion, as to the prompting of Advocats, but the Deponent minds not the particulars.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>collingtoun</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, was very intent and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the buſineſs of the Mint, but what privat intereſt he had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or if he had any, the Deponent knows not.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Reidfoord</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That my Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> did preſide as one that was ſerious in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and the Deponent looked upon him as earneſt to bring the Proceſs to a cloſe.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Forret</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, appeared to be more concerned than uſually he did in ordinary Proceſſes. And in Anſwer to the <hi>7th.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That the then Chancellor his carriage to the Lords, and the words he then ſpoke to them were unuſual, but cannot condeſcend upon the words.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Salin</hi> to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That he heard the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, reſume the Debates, and very fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urge theſe grounds, which did agree moſt to his own opinion.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Pitmedden</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That in the time that he was preſent at the Debates in the Inner-Houſe, he heard the Earl of <hi>Aderdene</hi> then Chancellor, deſire the Advocats that were imployed againſt <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> to ſpeak to certain Points that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf propoſed, but remembers not whether they were formerly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Advocats on either ſide.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, Depones, That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, did behave himſelf with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and forwardneſs in the Proceſs of the Mint, more than he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to do in other Proceſſes; and at the time of the Debate, he did ſeveral times ſuggeſt, or propoſe to the Lord Advocat Grounds and Reaſons, to be urged againſt the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and Officers of the Mint.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lords having after the Debate given their Interlocutor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent the Copper-Coyn; and of which Interlocutor, the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> had gotten a Copy from the Clerk. The Earl of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdene</hi> cauſed ſome days thereafter, alter the Interlocutor, and was angry with the Clerk for giving a Copy thereof.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>3d.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That the firſt Article of the Libel anent the Copper-Coyn, having been Debate, the Lords gave their Interlocutor, whereby they Repelled the Defences, founded upon the King's exoneration and Act of Indemnity; and found that the ſame could not ſecure the Defenders from being ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in reſtitution <hi>in quantum ſunt locupletiores facti,</hi> by the profits of the Copper-Coyns, more than was contained in the Warrands; and the Deponent having written the Interlocutor in theſe Terms (a Copy whereof he now produces, written by Sir <hi>Patrick Hume</hi>'s Mans hand, as the Deponent conceives) the Deponent did immediatly after writing thereof, ſhew the ſame to the Lord Advocat, who was ſatisfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175738:4"/>and then the Deponent gave a Copy of it to the Earl of <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> who had called for it; But Sir <hi>Patrick Hume,</hi> who was imployed in that Proceſs for the King's intereſt, having ſeen the Interlocutor, he about two days thereafter told the Deponent that it behoved to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified: and theſe words, <hi>in quantum ſunt locupletiores facti,</hi> left out: And in the Outter-Houſe, he gave the Deponent a Note, or Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum, for altering the Interlocutor, to be offered to the Earl of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdene,</hi> which Note the Deponent then gave to the ſaid Earl, then ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the Bench, who having immediatly moved the matter to the Lords; the Interlocutor was altered, and made in the Terms as it now ſtands in the Decreet; and immediatly thereafter, the Proceſs being called, and the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Advocats having Debated ſomething further anent the Point of the Copper-Coyn, they founded upon the Interlocutor as it was firſt written by the Deponent, and whereof they had gotten a Copy (which Copy they offered to produce) whereupon the then Lord Chancellor did ſharply rebuke the Deponent, for giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> a Copy of the ſaid Interlocutor; but does not remember that he diſcharged the Deponent to give any more Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of Interlocutors to the ſaid Earl; but the Deponent having receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the foreſaid Check, and the cauſe being of importance, and carried on for the King's intereſt (as the Deponent conceived) he reſolved to give no more Copies of Interlocutors in that Proceſs, until Sir <hi>Patrick Hume</hi> ſhould firſt ſee them.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Pitmedden</hi> to the <hi>4th.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That he did ſee the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> cauſe alter an Interlocutor Judicially, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the Clerk for having given out a Copy of the Interlocutor.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> cauſed Vote <hi>John Falconer</hi> the Warden's ſingle Depoſition, to be a ſufficient probation againſt the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> albeit it was formerly voted, not to be ſufficient.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>medden</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>5th.</hi> Interrogator, Depones, That when the Probation came to be Adviſed, the Queſtion was moved, whether the Teſtimony of <hi>John Falconer</hi> Warden, being but a ſingle Witneſs, could be a Probation, The Deponent being then to Vote in the Cauſe, deſired of the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, to call the Advocats to Debate that Point, how far a ſingle Witneſs in any caſe could prove, in regard the Deponent was unwilling to give a Vote againſt the King, ſo long as he had hopes to be cleared; and this deſire being refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the Queſtion being put to the Vote, the Deponent Voted, that a ſingle Teſtimony did not prove, and it was ſo carried by plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Votes. After which the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> did ſay, in theſe, or the like words, (Is this the way, my Lords, you guide the King's Affairs, this muſt be repreſented) and the Deponent Anſwered, God bleſs the King, it were happy for the Lords, that his Majeſty were often among them, to behold their Actions; And the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> Anſwered the Deponent in theſe, or the like words, how come you to anſwer more than the reſt: And thereafter the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> did repreſent to the Lords, that this Vote ſeemed to be contrair to a former Vote whereby the Lords had found my Lord <hi>Lauderdale</hi> lyable for the faults of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. By which the Deponent ſuppoſing, that the Earl meaned that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlocutor,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175738:4"/>which was pronounced when the Deponent was Ordinar in the Outer-Houſe. He Anſwered to the Earl, that he did not know of that Interlocutor, and therefore could ſay nothing of it. And the Lord <hi>Hercarſs</hi> deſired the Earl to make his beſt uſe of it: And the Deponent doth not remember diſtinctly what followed, whether there was a ſecond Interlocutor, or Vote, or how the Interlocutor was Dictated; for the Deponent was a little diſcompoſed with what had paſt betwixt the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and him in the Premiſſes, and ſo took not notice.</p>
            <p>My Lord Chancellor <hi>Perth</hi>'s Depoſition to the 4. Interrogator, which is inſerted in the Probation of the 3. Article, is repeated likewiſe in this place.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Reidfoord</hi> in Anſwer to the 3. Interrogator, Depones, that he remembers <hi>John Falconer</hi> the Warden, his Oath was Voted not to be a ſufficient Probation; and that the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſeemed to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content at the Vote, and ſaid it was the King's Intereſt, and if the Lords pleaſed, they might Aſſoilȝie my Lord <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> or the Officers of the Mint; but remembers not whether he expreſt one or both of them: And that thereupon there was an Overture made, that it was ſufficient againſt <hi>John Falconer</hi> himſelf. And the whole Officers being found lyable <hi>in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidum,</hi> it might be looked upon as a ſufficient Probation upon that Head; and the Deponent thinks it was ſo carried by plurality of Votes in a ſecond Vote.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon,</hi> to the 4. Interrogator, Depones, that at the Adviſing of the Probation, ſome of the Lords having demurred as to that Point, if the ſingle Depoſition of <hi>John Falconer</hi> Warden of the Mint, was ſufficient to prove the quantity of Copper Coyned in the firſt Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> did appear diſpleaſed, and in paſſion, uſed theſe expreſſions to the Lords that this was not his Intereſt, but the King's Cauſe, and if the Lords pleaſed, they might Aſſoilȝie the Earl of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale,</hi> or uſed words to that purpoſe. And thereafter it being put to the Vote, The Lords found the ſaid Depoſition was Probative upon that ground, that he being an Officer of the Mint, and Deponing upon a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter incumbent to his Office and Charge, his Depoſition did ſufficiently prove againſt himſelf, and conſequently againſt the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> as being lyable for him and the reſt <hi>inſolid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in the terms of a formal Interlocutor, and doth not remember that that Point was <hi>tune</hi> Voted, or not, nor yet how the Votes ran, but that it was carried by plurality of Votes; And Depones, that upon the Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi>'s uttering the foreſaids expreſſions, my Lord <hi>Pitmedden</hi> ſaid, that he wiſhed the King were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times preſent to hear them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam Chryſtie</hi> Depones, that at the Adviſing of the Probation, ſome of the Lords ſaid, that <hi>John Falconer</hi> Warden, ſeemed to be Examined before the Commiſſion as a Witneſs, as appeared by the ſtyle of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; (bearing, <hi>John Falconer</hi> of ſuch an Age, Depones.) And next, albeit he were Examined as a Party, ſome of the Lords ſaid, it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bateable how far it ſhould operate againſt another, albeit it were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation againſt himſelf. And after ſome Debate amongſt the Lords, the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſeemed to be angry and diſpleaſed, ſaying, My Lords, This is not my private concern, but the King's Cauſe. (If you will, for my part you may Aſſoilȝie the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>) And afterward it was carried <hi>affirmative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:175738:5"/>5. Albeit by the Interlocutor, the Lords found the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> only lyable for the reſt of the Officers of the Mint, <hi>in ſolidum quoad</hi> the Bulȝeon; yet after the Interlocutors were drawn upon the Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Probation, the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> cauſed apply the Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors as to the Bulȝeon, to the whole other Articles of the Libel, &amp; found the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> lyable <hi>in ſolidum,</hi> for the whole malverſations of the reſt of the Officers of the Mint.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Queensberry</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d</hi> Interrogator Depones, as to the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi>'s urging, that the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and his Son might be found lyable for the reſt of the Officers of the Mint. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent doth not remember the Argument he made uſe of to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Reidfoord,</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>2d</hi> Interrogator, Depones, that he thought my Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> earneſt to have every one of the Officers of the Mint found lyable <hi>in ſolidum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon,</hi> in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, Depones, That the time of the Adviſing, the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> was of the opinion, and did urge that the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> ſhould be found lyable <hi>in ſolidum</hi> for the other Officers of the Mint.</p>
            <p>To the 4, 5, 6, and 7. ſpecial Interrogators, Depones, that after the Deponent had drawn the Interlocutor, given upon Adviſing the Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sir <hi>Patrick Hume</hi> did draw another Draught of the Interlocutor in more ample terms, and in ſpecial, as to the ſeveral Officers of the Mint, their reſpective malverſations; and therein the Interlocutor which was given upon debate, as to the ſecond Article anent the Bulȝeon (finding the general Libel <hi>in ſolidum</hi> for the reſt of the Officers of the Mint) is applyed and repeated, as to all the Articles of the Libel relating to the Mint; Which Interlocutor Sir <hi>Patrick</hi> did ſhew to the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> the Deponent being preſent: And after the ſame was read, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent told he was not clear to Extract the Decreet in the terms of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlocutor, unleſs the ſame were brought to the Lords, and conſidered; Whereupon the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> ordained the Deponent to Tranſcribe that Interlocutor, and to bring it in to be read before the Lords the next day, which the Deponent did accordingly: And the Interlocutor being read, the Lords did acquieſce thereto, and the Decreet was Extracted conform to the ſamen.</p>
            <p>The King declared, he would not have the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> inſiſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; whereupon my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> Compeared at the Bar, and declared he could not Defend, and diſcharged his Advocats to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and gave in a written Declaration and Submiſſion to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Yet notwithſtanding he is made Compearing, and no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice is taken of his Declaration, and refuſal to Defend, but is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned <hi>in ſolidum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord Chancellor <hi>Perth,</hi> in his Anſwer to the 6. Interrogator, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones, That in the Council held at <hi>Windſor</hi> (where were preſent, beſide the Counſellors of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation) Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifax,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Sunderland,</hi> the now Lord The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurer of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. The late King, of ever bleſſed memory, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that what-ever faults might be in the Family of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175738:5"/>the Officers of the Mint, he thought my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> was not chargeable with any of them.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Belcarras,</hi> in his Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, Depones, That he was in a <hi>Scots</hi> Council at <hi>Windſor,</hi> where the late King's Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, after hearing the report of the Commiſſion anent the Mint, ſaid, That my Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> (to whom his Majeſty had ſpoken) was but a young Man, and had been much out of the Countrey, and therefore thought he had little meddling in that Affair; and his Majeſty ſaid, he thought he ſhould not be meddled with; and that after ſome debate in the Council about that matter, the Deponent thought it was his Majeſties reſolution, that my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> ſhould not be meddled with in that Affair.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in Anſwer to the firſt Interrogator, Depones, that the late King's Majeſty, in a <hi>Scots</hi> Council held at <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle, the 24. of <hi>August</hi> 1682. After hearing the report of the Commiſſioo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent the Mint read and conſidered, and that ſome in that Council had moved, that the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> might be turned out of his Office of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing General of the Mint, als well as the other Officers; His Majeſty did ſay, that my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> could not be guilty of any malverſations in his truſt of the Mint, ſince his Majeſty knew, that for the moſt part he was out of the Kingdom, by his Majeſties own allowance, and that he was very young: So if when at home any errors were committed by him, they were to be imputed to his Father, under whoſe conduct he was; and therefore his Majeſty declared, he would not ſuffer my Lord <hi>Mait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be meddled with, or touched in that Proceſs. All which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſpoke, with a great deal of zeal and concern for the Lord <hi>Mait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s intereſt.</p>
            <p>The Viſcount of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> in Anſwer to the 7. Interrogator, Depones, that in the Council at <hi>Windſor,</hi> the Deponent heard the late King ſay, he would not have the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> purſued for the Mint, or ſome words to that purpoſe: But what the Deponent heard his Majeſty ſay in private, the Deponent conceives he is not bound to declare it.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Forret,</hi> in Anſwer to the 6. Interrogator, Depones, that the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> did appear before the Lords, and declared in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that he would not Defend in the Mint-Proceſs, and diſcharged his Advocats to compear therein for him, and gave in a Declaration to that purpoſe in Writ.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> in Anſwer to the 6, Interrogator, Depones, that the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> did compear before the Lords, and declared, that he would not Defend in that Proceſs of the Mint, nor allow Advocats to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend for him, but referred himſelf to the King.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Reidfoord,</hi> in Anſwer to the 6. Interrogator, Depones, that the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> did appear, and declare, that he would not defend in the Mint-Proceſs, nor allow appearance for him againſt his Majeſty; and believes he did offer a Declaration or Submiſſion, or ſome Writ to that purpoſe, but it was refuſed at that time: But doth not remember whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lords opinion was asked or not.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Salin</hi> to the 6. Depones, that the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the Bar, and did inſinuat by diſcourſe to the Lords, his own innocency, and little acceſſion to the miſmanagment of the Mint, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175738:6"/>that his late Majeſty did very well underſtand it; and declared he would not defend in that Proceſs, but be ſilent and abſent.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> to the 2. Interrogator, Depones, that when the day of my Lord <hi>Maitlands</hi> compearance was come (he being out of the Countrey the time of the Citation of the reſt of the Defenders) and he being called, he did declare in preſence of the Lords, that he would not defend in that Proceſs, nor allow Advocats to appear or defend for him, but ſubmitted himſelf to the King's Majeſty, and gave in a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration Subſcribed by him to that purpoſe, which is in the Deponents hands: But it was found by Interlocutor, that the Lords could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Submiſſion from the Lord <hi>Maitland;</hi> and that he being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned with his Father in the Commiſſion, the Proceſs behoved alſo to go on againſt him; and remembers not whether this Interlocutor was pronounced before the Parties and Advocats were removed, or after; And in reſpect of that Interlocutor, the Deponent conceived he could not inſert the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> his Subſcribed Declaration in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet.</p>
            <p>To the additional Interrogator, Depones, that he had no expreſs war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand from the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> to mark my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> compear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor give out he Decreet againſt him as compearing; but Depones, that he having Written the Interlocutor, as to the Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it was pronounced, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Lords could not receive a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Lord <hi>Maitland;</hi> but being conjoyned with his Father in the Commiſſion, the Proceſs muſt alſo go on againſt him: And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he declined to propone any defences in the Cauſe, the Lords ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Libel to Probation againſt him; And the Act being Scrolled accordingly, Sir <hi>Patrick Home</hi> who had the managing of the Proceſs, did ſcore out theſe words, (In regard he declines to propone any Defences in the Cauſe) and cauſed Extract the Act againſt my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, as will appear by the Interlocutor, and Scroll of the Act, which are lying in Proceſs; whereunto the Deponent gave way, conſidering the truſt that Sir <hi>Patrick Home</hi> had in that Proceſs.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>James Dalrymple,</hi> in Anſwer to the 6. Interrogator, Depones, my Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> did compear, and made a gentile and diſcreet Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the terms of the Interrogator, remembers not, if he gave it in in Writ, or not, but remembers he ſaid, he would make no Defence, nor would allow Advocats to compear for him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Probation was not Voted ſeverally, in relation to every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, but joyntly, whether the Articles were proven or not.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon,</hi> in Anſwer to the 7. Interrogator, Depones, that at the Adviſing of the Cauſe, the Probation was pointed and read, as to every Article ſeverally; but to the beſt of the Deponents memory, there were only two Votes, one anent the Probation of the quantity of the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Coyned in the firſt Journey, and the other after the reading of all the Probation, as to the reſt of the Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam Chryſtie,</hi> before the end of his Depoſition, Depones, that after the Voting of <hi>John Falconer</hi> the Wardens Depoſition, the remanent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Libel ſeverally, one by one, and the Probation relative to every one of them was read <hi>in Praeſentia,</hi> and in the cloſe they were all Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175738:6"/>together, as the Interlocutor was Written thereupon: So that to the Deponents beſt memory, there was only two diſtinct Votes in Adviſing all the Probation.</p>
            <p n="8">8. After the Seſſion was up, the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> would have an Interlocutor added to the Decreet, which was not at all moved to the Lords, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Officers of the Mint ſhould be remitted by his Majeſty to the Lords of the Privy Council, or Juſticiary, to be puniſhed.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Alexander Gibſon,</hi> to the <hi>1ſt,</hi> and <hi>2d.</hi> of the 7. particular Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Depones, that after the Decreet was extended, and ready to be Subſcribed, Sir <hi>Patrick Home</hi> told the Deponent, that there was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion in the Libel, whereupon no Interlocutor was given, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Officers of the Mint be remitted to the Lords of Privy Council, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiary, to be puniſhed according to Law, for their malverſing; and did deſire the Deponent to inſert this following Clauſe in the Decreet, <hi>viz.</hi> As to that Concluſion of the Libel, whereby his Majeſties Advocat craves, that the late Officers of the Mint having committed ſuch manifeſt and groſs Acts of malverſation, in relation to the Mint, and their reſpective Offices, they ought to be remitted to the Lords of Privy Council, or Lords of Juſticiary, to be otherways puniſhed according to Law. The Lords ſuperceded to give Anſwer thereto, but remits the ſame to the King, that his Majeſty may do therein, and give further order thereanent, as he in his Royal Wiſdom ſhall think fit and expedient. And the Deponent having refuſed to inſert that Clauſe, in regard he had no warrand for it; Sir <hi>Patrick</hi> told him, that the Lord Chancellor expected it ſhould be done, and deſired the Deponent to ſpeak to him thereanent. And the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent having gone accordingly to the Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> told him, that Sir <hi>Patrick</hi> had deſired him to inſert the foreſaid Clauſe in the Decreet, which he conceived he could not warrantably do, ſeing there was no Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor for it. And the Earl ſaid to the Deponent, that there being ſuch a Concluſon in the Summons, it was neceſſary there ſhould be an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer given thereto, and ſaid, there was no hazard for the Deponent to inſert the ſaid Clauſe, there being nothing concluded thereby againſt the Defenders. And the Deponent Anſwered, he was not clear to do the ſame; and the Deponent thinking it would not have been further preſt, and having ſome buſineſs in the Country, went out of Town, reſolving to return at night; But about 3 or 4 hours thereafter in the ſame day, (being a <hi>Saturday</hi>) he received a Letter from a Servant in the Deponents Chamber, who wrote the Decreet, ſhewing him, that it was ſtill inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, that the ſaid Clauſe might be inſert in the Decreet, and that there was to be a meeting of the Lords of Seſſion to that effect that night, and deſired the Deponent to haſte in to the Town; and accordingly the Deponent having come, he went to Sir <hi>Patrick Home,</hi> who told him that he had ſpoken to my Lord <hi>Aberdene,</hi> who told him he was now content the Decreet ſhould be Extracted without that Clauſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> then Chancellor, was in uſe to threaten other perſons with Proceſs at the King's inſtance, but for his own ends.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:175738:7"/>
            <p>The Lord Chancellor <hi>Perth,</hi> in Anſwer to the 5. Interrogator, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones, that the Earl of <hi>Broad-Albane</hi> intreated the Deponent to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe with my Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> then Chancellor, that the Proceſs of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon intented againſt him might not go on, until the King were acquainted with the circumſtances of that matter. That my Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſpoke to the Deponent, of purchaſing his Lands in <hi>Caithneſs,</hi> which purchaſe he pretended he was deſigning ſometimes for the King (then Duke) and ſometime for Duke <hi>Gordon;</hi> though the Deponent hath good ground to believe ſince that it was not deſigned for either of them; and that the higheſt that ever he heard the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> offer, was 100000 pounds for the Earl of <hi>Broad-Albans</hi> whole intereſt in <hi>Caithneſs:</hi> And that the Deponent was informed, that the Proceſs went on anent the Forefaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or was ſtopt, according to the appearance of going on of that Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, or not. But when the Deponent ſaid to my Lord <hi>Aberdene,</hi> that it was not well to go on in that Proceſs againſt my Lord <hi>Broad-Albane,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King was better informed of the matter: And that my Lord <hi>Broad-Albane</hi> in ſtead of appearing to anſwer to the Criminal Proceſs, would go to <hi>London.</hi> The Lord <hi>Aberdene</hi> then ſaid, he ſhould not much trouble himſelf about that, for he would ſend up his Libel after him.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Queensberry</hi> to the laſt Interrogator Depones, he knows nothing of the Bargain betwixt the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and <hi>Broad-Albane,</hi> but what he heard from the Marqueſs of <hi>Athole:</hi> Only the Deponent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, that when the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> ſpoke to him of that Bargain, he pretended it was for the King or Duke, and ſtill ſhunned owing of it for himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Viſcount of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> in Anſwer to the 10. Interrogator, Depones, he knows there was a Treaty betwixt the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and <hi>Broad-Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bame,</hi> becauſe both Parties told the Deponent of it; but what was the Treaty, or the Price offered, the Deponent remembers not; but only the Deponent thought then it was a low price that was offered.</p>
            <p>Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> in Anſwer to the 8. Interrogator, anent the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain betwixt the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Marr,</hi> Depones, that the Deponent might have ſaid ſuch a thing to the Earl of <hi>Perth,</hi> as is mentioned in the Interrogator, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Deponent was afraid the Earl of <hi>Marr</hi> was like to loſe the Government of the Caſtle of <hi>Stirling,</hi> or his Regiment, if not both: But Depones, that if he ſaid it, it was out of no knowledge of any deſigns of the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> had to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the Earl of <hi>Marr,</hi> to part with ſeveral Superiorities in the North in his favours, or his threatning him with the loſs of his Regiment, or keeping the Caſtle of <hi>Stirling,</hi> or Tack of the Lordſhip thereof, upon the account of theſe Superiorities, and knew nothing of the Tranſactions betwixt them, anent the ſaids Superiorities.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:175738:7"/>
               <head>Octavo <hi>Novembris,</hi> 1682.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>SEDERUNT,</hi> Haddo <hi>Cancellarius,</hi> Newtoun <hi>Praeſes,</hi> Nairn, Tarbat <hi>Clericus</hi> Regiſtri, Collingtoun, Coſtlehill, Reidfurd, Pitmedden, Harcars, Saline, Boyne, Drumcairn <hi>&amp;</hi> Kemney.</head>
               <p>THe which day the Lord Chancellor produced a Letter from His Majeſty, direct to him, which being read, the Lords ordained the ſame to be Recorded in the Books of Sederunt; of which Letter the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor follows; <hi>Supraſcribitur. CHARLES R.</hi> Right Truſty and right well beloved Couſin and Counſellor, We greet you well; Whereas by Our Letter to you, bearing date at <hi>Windfor</hi> the twenty fifth of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> laſt by-paſt, upon Our hearing the two Reports fent unto <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi>s by the Commiſſioners, lately appointed by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> for the Tryal and Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the State of Our Mint, of that Our Antient Kingdom, We did ſignifie, that We had removed the perſons therein named, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from their reſpective Places and Offices in Our faid Mint; But alſo from all other Publick Offices and Imployments, which they did then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy under Us; And did likewayes order you to take care, that Our Council ſhould Command Our Advocat to proſecute them before competent Judges, either Civilly or Criminally, as accords of the Law; It is now Our Will and Pleaſure, and We do hereby Authorize and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you, to take care that Our Council Command Our Advocat to proſecute the therein mentioned Lord <hi>Hattoun,</hi> now Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> Sir <hi>John Falconer, Alexander Maitland,</hi> and <hi>Archibald Falconer,</hi> civilly before the Lords of Seſſion only, and when We ſhall have an Account of the Refult of that Civil Proceſs before them, We ſhall thereafter ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie Our Pleaſure concerning any further matter, that may be laid to their charge, in ſuch manner as to Us in Our Royal Wiſdom ſhall ſeem fit: And in regard We did not in Our ſaid Letter to you, of the <hi>25th.</hi> of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> laſt, make mention of <hi>John Falconer,</hi> the late Warden of Our ſaid Mint, notwithſtanding of his Malverſation (which clearly appears by the Report of Our ſaids Commiſſioners) during his long continuance in the Place of VVarden aforeſaid; It is alſo Our expreſs Pleaſure, that he be proſecute in the ſame manner and method, which VVe have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for the Proceſs againſt the perſons already mentioned: For do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all which, theſe Preſents to be Recorded, both in the Books of Our Privy Council, and of the Seſſion (if needful) ſhall be to you and them <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> and to all others who may be therein concerned, a ſufficient warrand: And ſo VVe bid you heartily Farewell. Given at Our Court at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> day of <hi>October,</hi> 1682. And of Our Reign the thirty fourth year. By His Majeſties Command <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:175738:8"/>
               <head>Double of the KING<hi>'s</hi> Letter, in favours of the Earl of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and Collonel <hi>Grahame, 1683.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the eighth day of <hi>May</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fourſcore three years, His Majeſties Letter underwritten, direct to <hi>William</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Queensberrie,</hi> Lord High Theſaurer for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>John Drummond</hi> of <hi>Lundie,</hi> Lord Theſaurer-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, was preſented and read, and ordained to be Booked; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Tenor follows. <hi>Sic ſupraſcribitur.</hi> CHARLES R. Right Truſty and right well beloved Couſin and Counſellor, and right Truſty and well beloved Counſellor, We greet you well, We have ſeen and fully conſidered the Decreet (bearing date at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 20 day of <hi>March</hi> laſt) obtained at the inſtance of Our Advocat, againſt <hi>Charles</hi> now Earl of <hi>Lauderdale, Richard</hi> Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> and the other Officers of Our Mint, of that Our Antient Kingdom, by which they are found juſtly lyable to Us in great and conſiderable Sums, much above what we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, they are able to pay, and are thereby fully convinced that their Malverſations, and Abuſes of their Truſt have been ſo great, that they ought not (for the terror of others) to paſs without ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: Yet out of Our Royal Goodneſs and Clemency, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ruine them and their Families, and calling to mind the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs of the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> in Our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, in ſeveral other ſtations, and the many good Services done to Us and Our Royal Anceſtors, by their Predeceſſors; We have now thought fit to let you know, that ſeing the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> did fully ſubmit to Our Determination, and have ſince humbly begged, and Petitioned Our Favour; It is therefore Our Will and Pleaſure, That the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> Diſpone to Our Right Truſty and right well beloved Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin and Counſellor, <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Aber dene</hi> Our Chancellor, in the moſt ample Form and manner, that he can in Law require, all and whole the Lands of <hi>Dudhope, Benvie</hi> and <hi>Balrudrie,</hi> and all others whatſomever, lying within ten miles of <hi>Dundee,</hi> which formerly did belong to the deceaſt Earl of <hi>Dundee,</hi> and have been ſince poſſeſſed by the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> or the Lord <hi>Maitland;</hi> and alſo, that they Diſpone to the ſaid Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> all Houſes, Tenements and Gardens, lying within the Town of <hi>Dundee,</hi> or <hi>Bonnot-Hill,</hi> belonging to them, with all the Right they have to the Paſſage on the Water of <hi>Tay,</hi> any manner of way, with the whole Profits and Emoluments thereof; as alſo the Right of Patronage of the Parſonage of <hi>Dundee,</hi> and all Superiorities and Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duties, or other Duties whatſomever, lying without the ſaid Town, within the bounds aforeſaid, which formerly did belong to the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſt Earl of <hi>Dundee,</hi> and were ſince poſſeſt by the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> or Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> Make full Right of, and Diſpone to Our right Truſty and well beloved Collonel <hi>John Grahame</hi> of <hi>Claver-houſe,</hi> The Houſe of <hi>Dudhope,</hi> with the Garden, Orchard, Park and Planting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent thereunto: as alſo the Office of Conſtabulary of <hi>Dundee,</hi> and all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175738:8"/>other Juriſdictions, Priviledges and Superiorities (and particularly the Rights, Priviledges and Emoluments of the firſt Fair) within the ſaid Town; Together with all other Rights, Profits and Emoluments there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in poſſeſt by the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> or Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly did belong to the ſaid Earl of <hi>Dundee,</hi> that are not there above particularly ordered to be Diſponed to the ſaid Chancellor. Providing always that the ſaid Collonel <hi>John Grahame</hi> pay to Our ſaid Chancellor twenty years Purchaſe for one years Liferent that can ariſe unto him by this Diſpoſition, which at any time hath been accompted for in the Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal books, as a part of theſe Lands, Diſponed to Our ſaid Chancellor: And it is Our further Will and Pleaſure, That the Rights of the ſaids Lands, Houſes, Juriſdictions and Superiorities, and others generally and particularly above-mentioned, as well in favours of Our ſaid Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, as of the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> be free of all Burdens and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumberances whatſoever, eſpecially the Warrandice of the Lands and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of <hi>Craig,</hi> the Lady <hi>Maitland</hi> her Joynture, and the depending Proceſs at the inſtace of the late Earl of <hi>Dundee</hi>'s Creditors; Or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways, That the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> or Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> Give ſuch Warrandice as ſhall be ſatisfactory to Our ſaid Chancellor, and the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> for their reſpective Securities in the Premiſſes: upon the performance of all which above-mentioned, We do hereby De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That We will give a full and general Indemnity, Remiſſion and Diſcharge to the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> in as ample Form and Manner, as in Law they can require, for any cauſe or offence, Civil or Criminal, in any publick ſtation preceeding the date hereof: Declaring likeways hereby Our expreſs Will and Pleaſure, that ſeing We have now ſhown ſo much Favour and Clemency to the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> they be firſt obliged to Diſcharge and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunce all ſuch Claim and Relief, that they as Generals of Our Mint, have, or could pretend againſt Sir <hi>John Falconer,</hi> late Maſter, Mr. <hi>James Falconer,</hi> Son and Heir to the ſaid deceaſt <hi>John Falconer</hi> late Warden, and the reſt of the late Officers thereof. And for further Security, We do hereby Aſſign and Diſpone to Our ſaid Chancellor, and the ſaid Collonel <hi>John Grahame,</hi> all Our Right, Title and Intereſt, in and to the ſaid Decreet againſt the late Generals of the Mint, with full Power to Purſue for, and recover the Sums contained therein, until Our ſaid Chancellor, and the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame</hi> ſhall be fully ſarisfied and payed of the ſum of 20000 <hi>lib. ſterling,</hi> in manner after ſpecified, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt 5000 <hi>lib.</hi> to Our ſaid Chancellor, and 2000 <hi>lib.</hi> to the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> and thereafter 11000 <hi>lib.</hi> to Our ſaid Chancellor, and 2000 <hi>lib.</hi> to the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame;</hi> Declaring nevertheleſs, That upon the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> their granting of the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Diſpoſitions, this right to the above mentioned Decreet, granted by Us to Our ſaid Chancellor, and the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> ſhall be void and null. So We bid you heartily Farewell. Given at Our Court at <hi>Windſor-Caſtle,</hi> 1. <hi>May</hi> 1683. and of Our Reign the <hi>35th.</hi> year. By His Majeſties Command, <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur,</hi> Middleton.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:175738:9"/>
               <head>Copy of the KING's Letter.</head>
               <head type="sub">To Our right Truſty and well beloved Couſin and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of Our Antient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sic ſupraſcribitur: CHARLES R.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>RIght Truſty and right well beloved Coufin and Counſellor, We greet you well, Whereas We are certainly informed, that the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> have fully Settled and Agreed with you, to your ſatisfaction of the Donations granted by Us unto you in Our Letter, bearing date at <hi>Windſor Castle,</hi> the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> laſt, directed to Our Theſaurer-Principal and Theſaurer-depute, and that in order to their fully ſatisfying Our right Truſty and well beloved Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, <hi>John Grahame</hi> of <hi>Claverhouſe,</hi> there was lately a Diſpofition of the Houſe, Garden and Park of <hi>Dudhope,</hi> and of the Office of Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulary of <hi>Dundee,</hi> ſigned by the ſaid Earl and Lady <hi>Maitland,</hi> at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and by the Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> in favours of the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> conform to the Tenor of Our ſaid Letter; And whereas We have ordered Our Secretaries to enquire, whether all Our Commands in Our ſaid Letter are obeyed; We find by them, that the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> have not as yet Diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Renunced all Sute, Claim and Relief, that they, as Generals of Our Mint, have, or could pretend againſt Sir <hi>John Falconer</hi> late Maſter, Mr. <hi>James Falconer</hi> Son and Heir to the deceaſt <hi>John Falconer</hi> late War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and the reſt of the late Officers thereof: And ſeing We have been graciouſly Pleaſed to ſhow ſo much of Favour and Clemency to the laid Earl and Lord, it would be moſt unreaſonable, als well as unjuſt, that they ſhould have recourſe to any Relief from the ſaid late Officers of the Mint, whom We have already ſo conſiderably Fined; For if this Relief were allowed, the ſaid Earl and Lord might thereby reap more advantage, than if they had not at all been called in queſtion, for any thing relating to the Mint. And now calling to mind, the many good and faithful Services performed by the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> and their Predeceſſors to Us and Our Royal Progenitors for ſeveral Ages; And being always no leſs ready and willing to confer marks of Our Royal Favour upon the Families of well deſerving Subjects, than to do Juſtice to all: We have ordered Our Secretaries to enquire of the Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> whether he will obey Our former Command, in diſcharging the ſaid Relief, who having declared that he is willing to ſubmit to Our Pleaſure; And We being very well ſatisfied with his ready and frank obedience to Our Commands herein; Therefore We have been graciouſly Pleaſed to ſign an ample and full Exoneration, Diſcharge, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Indemnity, in favours of the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to the ſaid Lord <hi>Maitland</hi> (both of the date of theſe Preſents) which We have ordered to be herewith ſent unto you: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175738:9"/>whereof, We do hereby authorize you to call for the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and to acquaint him, that as We have ſo graciouſly conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to do Our part, in favours of him and his Son: So We doubt not, but he will be ſo dutiful as to obey Our Commands, in diſcharging the ſaid Relief, and to allow him a weeks time for the performance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; At the expiring of which time, or ſooner, upon his giving obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this Our Command, We do Require you to call for the Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> Our Juſtice-Clerk, and the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame</hi> of <hi>Claver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> in his preſence, and to cauſe him (the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>) to Depoſit the ſaid Diſpoſition, and Diſcharge of the Relief aforeſaid, in the cuſtody of the ſaid Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> in Truſt, until the ſaids two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions ſhall be by you paſt under the Great Seal of the Our Antient Kingdom, which We do hereby require you to do with all poſſible and convenient ſpeed. And ſo ſoon as you ſhall have appended Our Great Seal to the ſaids two Remiſſions, it is Our further Will and Pleaſure, that you again call for the three forenamed perſons, with the ſaid Sir <hi>John Falconer,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Falconer,</hi> or any having authority from them, or for their behove, and ſee the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> for himſelf, the ſaid Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> and Lady <hi>Maitland,</hi> deliver the foreſaid Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as his and their proper and voluntar Facts and Deeds,) to the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> and to deliver the Diſcharge of the Relief aforeſaid, as his own proper and voluntary Fact and Deed, to the ſaid Sir <hi>John Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Falconer,</hi> or any other for their behove: And at the ſame time you are to deliver up the ſaids two Remiſſions (under Our Great Seal) to the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale.</hi> But if he ſhall refuſe to give ready obedience to theſe Our Commands, within the time already prefixed (which We do not expect) We intend not hereby to put the leaſt ſtop thereafter to any Diligence raiſed, or to be raiſed by the ſaid Collonel <hi>Grahame,</hi> againſt the ſaid Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and Lord <hi>Mait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for making Our ſaid Donation effectual unto him: And in that caſe (if it ſhall happen) it is Our Pleaſure, that ye return the ſaids two Remiſſions to Our Secretaries of State: For doing all which, this ſhall be your warrand: And ſo We bid you heartily Farewell. Given at Our Court at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the twenty fifth day of <hi>March,</hi> 1684. and of Our Reign the thirty ſixth year.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By His Majeſties Command, Sic ſubſcribitur,</hi> MIDLETOUN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:175738:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175738:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
